Manuel Madeira

PERSONAL DATA

EMAIL: manuel.madeira@epfl.ch Portugal CITIZENSHIP:

Website: manuel ml madeira. github. ioGITHUB: manuelmlmadeira LINKEDIN: manuel-madeira X: @manuelmlmadeira

ABOUT ME

I am a PhD student at EPFL working under the supervision of Pascal Frossard and Dorina Thanou. My research gravitates around generative modelling, graph deep learning, and how to leverage these to enable scientific discoveries, typically in the biomedical domain.

EDUCATION

2022 - Present	PhD. in Machine Learning École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne, Switzerland
2018 - 2019 (FALL)	Exchange student in Computer Science Tsinghua University, China
2018 - 2021	MSc. in Biomedical Engineering Instituto Superior Técnico, Portugal GPA: 19 / 20 (1st in class), Thesis: 20/20
2015 - 2018	BSc. in BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING Instituto Superior Técnico, Portugal GPA: 19 / 20 (1st in class and 1st ever to attain such grade)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE				
SEP 2022 - PRESENT	Doctoral Assistant at EPFL Studying the incorporation of domain knowledge into graph diffusion models. My research addresses graph generative models and the development of generation evaluation metrics for digital pathology.			
SEP 2021 - Aug 2022	Machine Learning Researcher at Inductiva Research Labs Conducted research on deep learning based approaches to solve partial differential equations. Deployed physics-informed neural networks to model heat diffusion and coastal dynamics and analysed their generalization to arbitrary domains.			
Mar 2021 - Jun 2021	Research Internship at Institute for Systems and Robotics Advisors: Renato Negrinho, João Xavier, and Pedro Aguiar Researched on L -smoothness exploitation for first-order stochastic optimization methods with theoretical developments on algorithmic analysis.			
SEP 2019 - FEB 2020	Research Internship at IST-ID Transcribed interviews on health technologies assessment in Portugal for the MEDI-VALUE PROJECT.			

AWARDS AND HONORS

2022-23	EDIC PhD Fellowship, by EPFL
2016-18	1st ranked student in Biomedical Engineering BSc, by Instituto Superior Técnico
2015-20	Diploma of Academic Excellence (Top 10%), by Instituto Superio Técnico
2009 - 15	Best student in high school, by Crédito Agrícola

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Network Machine Learning	Languages:	Python, Matlab, Java, Mathematica, R
• Probability and Statistics	Frameworks:	PyTorch, Keras, Tensorflow, Pan-
• Practice of Object-Oriented Programming		das, Scikit-learn, NumPy, CVX,
• Analysis I		CVXPY/CVXOPT, Abaqus

 Histology MISC: Unix, Git, Conda, Colab, Tmux, Pueue

SOFTWARE SKILLS

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] MM, D. Thanou, and P. Frossard. Tertiary Lymphoid Structures Generation through Graph-based Diffusion. In: *GRAIL Workshop*. MICCAI. 2023.
- [2] S. Moalla*, \mathbf{MM}^* , L. Riccio*, and J. Lee*. [Re] Reproducibility Study of Behavior Transformers. In: ML Reproducibility Challenge 2022. Outstanding Paper Award (Honorable Mention). ReScience C. 2023.
- [3] MM, R. Negrinho, J. Xavier, and P. M. Aguiar. COCO Denoiser: Using Co-Coercivity for Variance Reduction in Stochastic Convex Optimization. In: OPT2021 Workshop. NeurIPS. 2021.

Extracurricular Activities

2023 Attended Cambridge Ellis Unit Summer School on Probabilistic Machine Learning

2022- Co-organizer of Deep Learning Sessiong Portugal

2021 Attended Lisbon Machine Learning Summer School

2009-21 Competitive football player (national level)

2015 National finalist in Biology Olympiad

LANGUAGES

Personal Interests

Football, CrossFit, Reading, Cinema

PORTUGUESE: Native

ENGLISH: C2, TOEFL iBT: 114 / 120

SPANISH: A2 FRENCH: A2

Chinese: Elementary (Tsinghua course)